James B. Whipple Papers
James B. Whipple Papers
1953-1974
Whipple, James B., 1913-
3 linear ft.
Reports, drafts, correspondence, memoranda, outlines and proposals from the American educator and consultant. Most of the papers relate to Whipple’s position as senior partner of his consulting firm, New Directions for Education (1968-1973). In this capacity, Whipple became involved in major planning projects for higher education in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. There are also materials from his partners, Freda H. Goldman and Peter E. Siegle. In addition, there are some papers from Whipple’s tenure as assistant, later associate director of the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.
149436
Biographical History
James B. Whipple was the assistant and associate director of the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) from 1953 until it ceased to exist in 1968. At that time he, along with Peter E. Siegle and Freda H. Goldman, formed a partnership for consulting called New Directions for Education (NDE), which existed from 1968-1973. In this capacity, Whipple became heavily involved in major planning projects for higher education, including state plans in Rhode Island and Massachusetts. Later he became Assistant Professor of History at Bunker Hill Community College in Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection is predominantly reports, report drafts, working papers and other writings that resulted from Whipple's role as a consultant. In connection with these projects, there is also correspondence, memoranda, outlines and proposals. There is some material from his work with CSLEA as well as some from his other professional activities as speaker and educator. There is a picture of James Whipple in the NUEA Spectator, found in Box 3.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into five parts:
CSLEA: Dated from 1953-1968, most of this portion is about the project, Liberal Education for Executives
New Directions for Education: This encompasses the bulk of the collection, 1968-75. Following business papers, the material is filed alphabetically by project. The state plans are filed chronologically
Other Professional Activities: A variety of activities from the 1950s to 1978 are represented
Personal: Few odd papers for Whipple's personal life are in the collection
Publications: These include a small sample of material for which Whipple wrote prefaces or to which he contributed.
Reports and papers authored by Whipple are tagged with the parenthetical (JBW).
Related Material
The library also holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. Most closely related to the James B. Whipple Papers are the following:
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA)
Fund for Adult Education (FAE)
University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (UCEPR)
Separated Material
Several monographs and pamphlets were removed from the archive and placed in the general collection of the Syracuse University Libraries:
Alter, Henry C. Of Messages and Media: Teaching and Learning by Public Television. Boston, Mass.: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1968.
Carey, James T. Forms and Forces in University Adult Education. Boston, Mass.: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1961.
Gordon, Morton. Daytime School for Adults. A New Program Dimension at University of California, Berkeley. Boston, Mass.: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1967.
Miller, Harry L. Participation of Adults in Education. Boston, Mass.: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1967.
Ohliger, John. Listening Groups: Mass Media in Adult Education. Boston, Mass.: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1967.
Cleon, Sally. Changing Patterns in Continuing Education for Business. Boston, Mass.: Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1967.
Wedemeyer, Charles A. and Childs, Gayle B. New Perspectives in University Correspondence Study. Boston, Mass._ Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1961.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Goldman, Freda H.; Siegle, Peter E.; Whipple, James B., Archives; Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults; New Directions for Education; Adult education; Educational planning; Educators, United States; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Memorandums.; Outlines.; Reports.; Educational consultants.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James B. Whipple, 1983.
Inventory
- Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA)
  - Conference Reports
    - Nov. 10-13, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Progress Report, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Second Progress Report, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Liberal Education For Executives
    - Annual Report, Sect. III, undated (Box 1)
    - Misc. materials, 1953-1968 (Box 1)
    - Memos, misc., undated (Box 1)
    - Papers, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
    - Notes, drafts, undated (Box 1)
    - Proposal, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Papers, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - University of Rhode Island
    - Correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - CSLEA in Retrospect: A Final Report (Liveright, Alexander), 1968? (Box 1)
    - Proposal -- Continuing Education for Ministry, undated (Box 1)
    - Proposed Program for Master of Liberal Studies, 1968 (Box 1)
- New Directions for Education
  - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Income and expenses, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Invoices, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Partnership papers, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Taxes, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Academy for Educational Development (AED)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Outlines and overviews -- Continuing Education, undated (Box 1)
    - Questionnaire, forms, undated (Box 1)
    - Reports (and drafts), undated
      - Chapter 10, Engineering and Science (Box 1)
      - Chapter 12, Private Industry (Box 1)
      - Chapter 13, Federal Activity and Finance (Box 1)
      - Summary and Conclusions, Education for Women, Sources (Box 1)
  - Cooperative Extension (Mass.)
    - Case Studies, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - Proposals, memos, notes, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Misc., undated (Box 1)
    - Misc. -- Kansas City, Mo., undated (Box 1)
  - First National Bank, Boston, Mass., Training Program, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Goddard College
    - Clippings, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Course listings, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Outline, position paper, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Papers and articles, 1962; 1966,; 1972 (Box 1)
    - Pilot program, undated (Box 1)
    - Proposal, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Proposal, 1972; drafts (Box 1)
    - Misc., undated (Box 1)
  - Lesley College, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Board of Higher Education
    - Report, Special Commission, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Title I, Chap. 572, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Higher Education Facilities Commission
      - State Plan for Community Service and Continuing Education, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
      - Haygood Report, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Urban Institute, undated (Box 1)
    - Urban Observatories, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - A Revised State Plan for Community Service and Continuing Education, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Evaluation of Present Program and Recommendations for the Future (JBW), 1969 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Council for Title I
      - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
      - Memos, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Bibliographies, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - People -- Title I Agency, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Levin Report -- Continuing Education in Mass., 1970 (Box 1)
    - Master Plan, 1970-1972
      - Study Committees, 1970-1971
        - Working papers
          - Educational Support Services (Box 1)
          - Financing Higher Education (Box 1)
          - Organization of Higher Education (Box 1)
          - Quality of Faculty (Box 1)
          - Space Needs (Box 1)
          - Student Rights and Obligations (Box 2)
        - Preliminary Reports, Sect. I and II (Box 2)
      - Master Plan for Public Higher Education
        - Drafts, 1971
          - Human Needs and Social Purposes (Box 2)
          - VI. Organization, Faculty, Students (Box 2)
          - VII. Educational Support Services (Box 2)
          - VIII. Financial Needs (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Citizen's Advisory Committees, Recorder's Reports, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Report draft (JBW), supporting materials, 1971? (Box 2)
    - IMPACT, proposals, 1971-1972; forms (Box 2)
    - Publications
      - Annual amendments
        - 1969 (Box 2)
        - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
        - 1972 (Box 2)
        - 1972, IMPACT (Box 2)
        - New Hampshire, Title I, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Newsletters
        - Community service and continuing education
          - Vol I-III, incomplete, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
          - Notes, June issue, 1971 (Box 2)
          - Notes, December issue, 1971 (Box 2)
  - New England Board of Higher Education (NEBHE)
    - Student interns, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
  - Rhode Island Department of Education
    - Master plan, 1967-1974
      - Sabatino report, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Consultation pamphlets, undated (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Outline, notes, undated (Box 2)
      - Progress reports, undated (Box 2)
      - Proposals, Title I, recommendations, undated (Box 2)
      - Report -- Readiness for Change (JBW), undated (Box 2)
      - Title I
        - Program status report, meeting, 7 May 1970 (Box 2)
        - Proposal guidelines, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
        - Proposal and amendment, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Report drafts, notes, 1971-1973? (Box 2)
      - Freda Goldman, 1971-1972
        - Working paper, 1972 (Box 2)
        - Coordinating Council, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
        - Report drafts, meetings, memos, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Coordinating Council, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Report on process, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Invoices, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - Subcommittees, 1972-1973
        - Current Capabilities (Box 2)
        - Experimental Models (Box 2)
        - Systems of Coordination (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, memos, meetings, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - Misc., 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - Toward a Master Plan, Feb 1973; appendices (Box 2)
      - Highlights, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Phase I report, misc., Mar 1973 (Box 2)
      - Status study, report, undated (Box 2)
      - Misc., outlines, notes, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Technical Training Council, proposal, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Misc., 1974 (Box 2)
    - Community Welfare and Human Services
      - Notes, undated (Box 2)
      - Workshops
        - Planning Task Force, 1973 (Box 2)
        - Reports, 1973; 1974 (Box 2, 3)
        - Workshop II, 1974; draft report (Box 3)
        - Interim report II, Apr 1974 (Box 3)
        - Task Force, 1974 (Box 3)
        - Workshop III, background (Box 3)
        - Workshop III, 1974; paper, drafts (Box 3)
      - Links in Education, A Partial Study, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Draft Proposal -- An Integrated System of Continuing Education (JBW), 1974 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, Univ. of Maine, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Fundamental Adult Education Project
      - Notes, undated (Box 3)
      - Purposes, 1974? (Box 3)
      - Working paper, issues and prospects, 1974? (Box 3)
      - UNI-Center, Client Study, 1974-1975
        - Assessment, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Plan, Vol. II and III, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Position paper, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Reports, drafts, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Working paper (JBW) -- Client Study Data as a Basis for Program Development in Fundamental Adult Education, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Memos, meetings, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Proposal, name change, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Publications, sources, 1972 (Box 3)
  - University of Massachusetts, Boston
    - Metrocenter, 1965; 1968-1970; proposals, drafts (Box 3)
  - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (UCEPR)
    - Papers
      - Background material, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Higher Continuing Education for Public Responsibility (JBW), 1969?; draft (Box 3)
      - Higher Continuing Education in a Changing World, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 3)
- Other professional activities
  - Bunker Hill Community College
    - Proposal, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Ad Hoc Humanities Committee, 1976; memos (Box 3)
    - Alternative Liberal Studies, undated (Box 3)
    - Course proposal, 1976?; Humanism, drafts (Box 3)
    - Humanism, notes, undated; Fromm
      - Notes, background materials, undated (Box 3)
    - Proposal to Toyota Fund, 1978? (Box 3)
  - Knox Symposium
    - Addresses
      - 1972 (Box 3)
      - Notes, drafts, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Continuing Professional Education, Technical and General Objectives (JBW), 1972 (Box 3)
    - Background materials, program, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3)
  - University of Maine, Human Services Development Institute, 1974; 1974?; notes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Address Notes -- Unitarian Layman's League, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Bright idea file, undated (Box 3)
    - Book idea -- Presidential Bee, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1963; 1972 (Box 3)
    - History based on success motif -- ideas, undated (Box 3)
    - Notes for papers, undated (Box 3)
    - NUEA Spectator, Vol. 27, No. 5, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Quest for Security in America (JBW), 1950s; clippings (Box 3)
    - Theory and Curriculum, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
    - Univ. of Illinois, correspondence, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Misc., 1971 (Box 3)
- Personal
  - Correspondence, Florence Whipple, 1959-1962; will (Box 3)
  - Real Estate Exam, 1972 (Box 3)
- Publications
  - American Association of University Professors Bulletin, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - JBW contributions
    - CSLEA
      - 1953 (Box 3)
      - 1963 (Box 3)
      - 1968 (Box 3)
    - Syracuse University
      - 1969 (Box 3)
  - NDE partners
    - A Turning to Take Next -- Freda Goldman, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Beyond the Campus, Mass. B.H.E., 1971 (Box 3)